Which foods cause inflammation
and which foods reduce it?
And why does it matter?
That's what we'll be looking at
in this video and the next.
"Foods That Cause Inflammation
and Those That Reduce It"
Excessive inflammation may play a
role in a number of leading causes
of death and disability,
including type 2 diabetes,
obesity, and heart disease.
But what are the stimuli that jumpstart
the deleterious inﬂammatory cascade?
You typically hear about
the pro-inflammatory nature
of a chronic high-fat diet,
but the inflammatory effect
“may not be limited to chronic
intake but may be evident
after the consumption of a single meal.”
Within hours after eating an
unhealthy meal, inflammatory markers
like (IL-6), interleukin-6, can
skyrocket, doubling within six hours.
The majority of studies show an increase in IL-6
after the consumption of a high-fat meal.
But the meals they tested weren’t
just filled with meat, eggs,
dairy, and oil, but also junky refined carbs
like white flour and added sugar.
Yes, give people essentially
straight butter fat and no carbs,
and you can still get a spike
in inflammation within hours,
proving the added fat
itself is pro-inflammatory.
But give people straight
sugar water without any fat,
and you can get the same
thing, proving the added sugar
is pro-inflammatory too.
Why should we be concerned with
the inﬂammatory responses
after unhealthy meal ingestion?
Because substantial research
points to the notion that
persistent low-grade inﬂammation
is an underlying factor
in several high-mortality chronic
diseases, and that diet
can contribute to, or
attenuate, that inﬂammation.
You’ll note in this graph that IL-6
levels jumped up to about 3 pg/mL.
You start regularly getting
up to levels of about 3 pg/mL,
and that’s associated with
twice the risk of death.
That increased risk was found across the board,
compiling eight other similar
studies, likely because
it’s linked with increased
risk of heart disease,
the #1 killer of men and women,
even about as strongly as
some other major established
risk factors like high cholesterol.
Now, not all high-fat
foods cause inflammation.
More than a dozen studies combined
show that whole plant foods
such as nuts do not
increase inflammatory markers,
even eating up to handfuls of nuts a day.
In fact, spread half an
avocado on a beef burger,
and you may be able to blunt
some of the inflammation
caused by the meat—even lean meat.
There are reviews purporting to show
a drop in inflammatory markers
after eating wild game, which is
about as lean a meat as you can get,
but that’s only compared
to store-bought meat.
Give people some really fatty meat,
and their IL-6 shoots up,
as does their tumor-necrosis
factor and C-reactive protein.
Inflammatory, inflammatory, inflammatory
within hours of it going into your mouth.
But what if you instead
eat a kangaroo steak,
extremely low fat on the
order of elk or moose?
What you get is inflammatory,
inflammatory, inflammatory
again within hours of it
going into your mouth.
Now, certainly less inflammatory
than conventional meat
you might get at the store, but
pro-inflammatory nonetheless,
increasing markers of
inflammation within mere hours.
“Intervention studies to
enhance healthy ageing need
appropriate outcome measures,
such as blood-borne biomarkers,
which are easily obtainable, cost-
effective, and widely accepted.”
We need blood-borne
biomarkers of mortality risk.
For example, having higher levels of
C-reactive protein in your blood
ay increase your risk of dying
prematurely by 42 percent.
C-reactive protein is the most
widely used inﬂammatory biomarker
for predicting mortality, but those
with the highest levels of (IL-6),
interleukin-6, another marker of
inflammation, may increase
premature death risk 49 percent.
What can we do to bring it down?
In my last video, I talked about
foods we eat that can contribute
to inflammation like meat and sugar,
versus foods like nuts that don’t.
But what about anti-inflammatory foods that
actually attenuate that inflammation?
Let’s see what happens
when you add blueberries
to a high-fat meal with a high glycemic load.
White potatoes, white bread, ham,
cheese, butter, and more cheese,
with or without a single
cup of blueberries.
Add blueberries and get a significant
drop in IL-6 from that meal.
What about raspberries? Feed people
eggs, butter, white potatoes,
white flour biscuits, and
sausage with or without two cups
of frozen raspberries blended
with water into a smoothie,
compared to giving people
the same amount
of calories and carbs in banana form and...
bananas were no match for the
meat, eggs, dairy, and crappy carbs;
that resulted in a tripling of
IL-6 levels within four hours.
But instead, drink those two cups of raspberries,
and your body is able to hold the line.
Why did raspberries work
whereas bananas didn’t?
Maybe it’s the antioxidants?
Well, antioxidant supplements failed miserably–
no benefit from antioxidant vitamins and minerals
like vitamins C, E, beta-
carotene, or selenium.
Maybe it’s those special antioxidant
pigments, the anthocyanins
that give berries those bright
red, blue, and purple colors?
And indeed, that’s what
dozens of randomized
controlled trials have demonstrated.
Whereas a half dozen studies
combined show pomegranates,
a fruit packed with anthocyanin pigments,
can bring down inflammation over time.
What about adding spices to meals
as an approach to cool down inflammation?
Supplementation with grape
and turmeric extracts did not
affect the inflammatory
response to a milkshake.
But give people actual turmeric,
one teaspoon a day of the whole spice,
and you get a significant drop in IL-6 levels,
but not when you just give people
purified curcumin supplements.
Garlic powder reduced IL-6 levels as well,
starting at about a half teaspoon a day.
And ginger powder (just ground ginger)
showed the same thing,
with doses ranging from half a
teaspoon to one and a half teaspoons.
Of course, another way to
mediate the inflammation
caused by a Sausage and Egg McMuffin
is to not eat it in the first place.
What about just eating a plant-based diet?
To my surprise, the drop in IL-6 did
not reach statistical significance.
Whenever a dietary intervention
doesn’t have the result you expect,
you always have to ask,
“What was the diet they exactly ate?”
The study mostly looked
at the Mediterranean diet,
which certainly has more plants,
but maybe the diets didn’t go far enough?
To figure that out, we can
turn to Dr. Turner-McGrievy’s
famous New DIETs study where
people either continued to eat
their fully omnivorous diets or
were randomized to eat a vegan diet,
a vegetarian diet,
a pesco-vegetarian diet,
or a semi-vegetarian diet that,
for example, limited red meat.
So, whereas the vegan might
eat red beans and brown rice
with chopped tomatoes and
roasted peppers for dinner,
the ovo-lacto-vegetarian
might add some cheese,
the peso-vegetarian might add shrimp,
and the semi-vegetarian might
have some turkey sausage.
What happened within two months to their
Dietary Inflammatory Index scores?
The Dietary Inflammatory Index
is a measure of how
inflammatory your diet is.
Negative scores mean your overall
diet is anti-inflammatory
and the lower the better,
whereas positive scores mean
your diet is on balance pro-inflammatory.
And that’s exactly where
they all started out.
No surprise, as they
were eating regular diets,
and our nation is awash with
inflammation-related disease.
But ask people to switch to
strictly plant-based nutrition,
and their diet flips to become
an anti-inflammatory diet.
And that was the case even
if they just cut out meat,
or just all meat except fish.
But have them instead switch mostly
to poultry, or simply limit their
meat intake, and their
diet remains inflammatory.
Now, not all plant-foods
are anti-inflammatory.
If all you do is boost your intake
of less healthy plant foods,
like juice, white bread, white
potatoes, soda, and cake
you can end up even more inflamed.
But if you eat a really clean
diet of whole plant foods,
not only do you get a significant
reductions in Lp(a)
(which we didn’t even think
was possible with diet),
as well as drops in LDL cholesterol, of course,
and even the most dangerous
form of LDL cholesterol,
but nearly across the board you also
get a drop in inflammatory markers.
We’re talking a 30 percent
drop in C-reactive protein,
a 20 percent drop in IL-6.
So, maybe previous studies
utilizing plant-centered diets
were unsuccessful because they
weren’t plant-based enough,
with animal products still being
substantially consumed.
The total elimination of animal
products and processed foods
may therefore be a more prudent dietary
strategy to combat inflammation.